today the the uh first moving to the uh
introduction of uh speech
recognition which is kind of main part
of uh this uh
director
so we have a couple of agenda today one
is that the to try to do the kind some
demonstration of
speech and the uh we also introduce the
measure performance measure how to kind
of evaluate uh our speech is good or not
and we also discuss about how we obtain
the
transcriptions uh and I will also
briefly explain about database and then
today in the last part I will also
explain about the weekly uh assignment
the
homework okay so let's move to the uh
the uh the general introduction uh the
automatic speech recognition as everyone
here may know now the uh the task is to
convert the web form to text uh like
using the CD or the Google or whatever
to convert the some kind of Text uh
Speech information to a text information
so that's uh the try to uh do some
demonstration like English Google Voice
SE I
have
rep so wait a moment
we need to change this
one I want to go to the CMU
campus Carnegie melon University is 7
minutes from your location this is a
good the spe question right well let's
try to kind of do bit more
test I want to go to the C campus
Carnegie melon university is S minutes
from your location by car in heavy our
Google colleagues are doing well but
let's try to do bit more hard one um
okay so I usually try to make a noise by
myself uh there uh like for example
I want to go to the CMU
campus minutes from your location by car
in heavy traffic here are your
directions I think for this particular
one uh made the since it is the the uh
the uh the G kind of sign in and also
the at least this one should not have
such kind of adaptation function as far
as I know yeah they might do something
but basically they don't have so still
the performance very good I still try to
find the way to kind of for them to
fail let's try to make a noise bigger
noise I this is my voice example of this
one and this one is uh the same eror con
and I want to go to the CM
campus
car minutes from your location by car in
heavy traffic your
directions I try to find the example
that it is paying but it seems like our
our friend the people in Google are
doing very
well okay so next maybe I can also
change the setting and change the
language um
it was not easy
actually Japanese
somewhere I can only speak English and
Japanese to apologize that
the example
is based in
[Music]
Japanese sorry find
now it becomes
Japanese that's actually perfect yeah
please trust me
okay so uh I I did a couple of
experience experiments here and I wanted
to find some kind of a the fav example
but I couldn't show you that guys but uh
the last time I did several other try
out and I found this kind of mistakes
are
the little similar but it's actually
having some mistakes and the uh same for
the uh Japanese cases um the there's
some kind of mistakes that I also found
and then uh the um yeah if perfectly
working it is fine but uh the technology
is sometimes that are making the problem
difficult in the kind of adverse
conditions and then that we want to
actually evaluate the performance of
speech recognition so uh the first part
of this lecture is starting about how to
kind of evaluate the performance
so the first uh the evaluation metc is
the sentence
error regard regardless of whether the
other part is kind of correct if some
some part of the sentence is wrong uh
this becomes the wrong this sentence
error is quite kind of intuitive and
probably the people may first thinking
that this is the kind of a measure for
speech recognition uh right and this is
actually a good measure there but at the
same time as you see that uh only this
part is wrong right and the other part
is actually correct but making
everything to be done wrong is a kind of
a not the little bit too close measure
so people usually don't use the sentence
the error rate so much uh instead the
people are using the
word for example in this case uh we have
these two kind of a like the world are
wrong right and then uh there is kind of
two the this two can become a c and that
and CMU not sure but exactly but may
become a uh that become a and this part
is actually missing so there are kind of
the two types of error in this example
this part is called substitution errors
and this part is called the division
error
and then in this kind of example we have
a three uh error count and then we can
compute the the word error rate and
divided by the number of the reference
word 1 two 3 4 five 6 7 8 and then the
the error becomes
37.5% so this are kind of a definition
that people widely use uh in the spe
conition however uh this is not always
kind of a easy to apply in some
languages uh for example the Japanese
cases and the mandar and so on uh we
usually don't hover uh the the the the
the water
boundary and then water boundary can be
depending on the system or definition of
the the some the linguistic the manner
and so on so it's not easy to actually
get the world boundary in this case uh
people also often using the uh character
uh error dat uh and in this example the
we just have two characters I don't know
how you guys uh the uh the recognize but
anyway this is one character and this is
one character and uh this cases there
are two other characters that are
corresponding to the error and then in
this case the character error is the uh
divided by the uh the
uh uh number of the the characters here
uh the in in the denominator and it
becomes
11.1% um however this uh the the
substitution delion uh insertion is
actually not easy to compute in general
we have to have some kind of
alignment of you know this part to be
same this part to be same and identify
which part would be errors and so on so
this uh the part is not easy to compute
but fortunately we have a lot of kind of
algorithm to solve this and one of the
most famous approach is that the r Stein
distance edit distance computation and
this is the the try to kind of get to
the the insertion delion substitution
error combination uh as a kind of a
minimum number uh in the in the all
possible kind of a candidate of the the
error butons so this one is actually at
the quite kind of efficiently computed
by using the the algorithm so I will
explain about it so first we write the
the reference and hypothesis as a matrix
okay and then we
inserted uh one additional
line one additional column and one
additional
row these are the extra row cor
responding to the case that there is no
for example the no output in the
reference or no output in the
hypothesis and then uh we can actually
the compute the the the Errors By The
the checking this kind of a the table
and then Computing the each error and so
on and usually using this kind of
equations this the equation is
correspond in to the insertion error
divition error and substitution error
and I will explain each of the the error
more detail so first uh the the each of
the point corresponding to the kind of
matching of the uh the reference and
hypothesis so for example this part the
here this element corresponding to
there's no hypothesis and there's no
reference and this point here is that
there's no refence but the hypothesis
has a c and this this part is actually
having a hypothesis the C A and the
reference is nothing so by the adding
this kind of exterra the the column we
can actually have a case that there's no
refence and there is no hypothesis and
how we can compute the error again this
is a case where here there's no
difference and then having the
hypothesis this is a kind of a extra
word we generated right and which
correspond to the the error one one
error and two count of the error and
three count of error and we also have
opposite cases for example the
difference is this kind of four the word
but the system doesn't output
anything and then uh this is
the one the missing word two missing
word three missing word four missing
word so each element are corresponding
to the kind of error what kind of error
it occurred and this part of the the uh
the additional kind of extra line is
easy we just kind of accumulating the
error right and then this other
corresponding to the uh the insertion
eror and the dation
error but this is not the the the
entirey through because actually
hypothesis is go to the from the the uh
the here and defance is also here we
actually want to find uh the the error
account in the last part this the right
corner and then how to get it we
actually consider all possibility for
example starting from here and then
going to
right going to right means that we also
have additional kind of the uh
additional the hypothesis and then this
can be a additional insertion error and
then this is the adding from one to one
and it becomes
two another possible Direction it comes
from here to here and then D can be from
one to one and equal two and another
possible error is comes from here to
here diagonal line and in this cases the
substitution or the error is actually in
this case that there's no kind of error
so it can be zero but the here the C and
two is different so we actually adding
one so this are the the each of the the
part corresponding to the arrow of the
from the the left to right is the this
first line or are the the top to bottom
is second line and then the third line
is
substitution and each of the PA we try
to find the minimum uh the the the uh
the error and then in this cases
substitution case the still the error
count is one so we actually are using
this one as uh
the uh other error Point
here and then by continuing this kind of
of computation we could actually get the
all the kind of the error count in the
table incrementally and then uh we can
actually compute all the other error in
this cases actually the error is
three however uh and then the after that
we can uh actually find that for example
by considering this
route uh we have a two sub substitution
error and the one uh
the uh the one ER that is
missing or the the other case is also
the happens uh we can still have a this
kind of R so in this Cas is the first
part is the substitution error and then
second part is delis error and the third
part is the sitution error so actually
this uh error pattern is not unique this
is also
not so just want to kind of recap this
computation lein distance is can
actually go to 100 over the 100% error
so because if we have a lot of the
repetition of the world it would have a
lot of insertion errors insertion error
counts right which actually goes to more
than uh the the uh the original number
of count in the reference so it's go to
over 100 and as I mentioned this uh
breakdown is not unique so it can be
kind of a the the uh in substitution
substitution derision or the
substitution D substitution either also
happens but both cases the error count
is
three so we actually cannot identify it
Al some rules to fix kind of order but
basically we cannot fully identify uh
this F part is the substitution uh the
the D and so
on so uh the but still uh this is a very
good measure uh for example I often ask
the we'll ask you guys to check this
kind of a number please check insertion
erors please check the d erors please
check the substitution errors so
substitution error is more kind of a
intuitive right that that saying
something wrong but if the Very extreme
insertion error happens like for ex this
case the system the repeat it I want to
go to I want to go to I want to go to is
sounds like there are some kind of
Errors uh in the kind of system Behavior
right so in this case actually easy to
detect what happening and the same for
the delion cases it's the extremely
small maybe are the the issues again not
only for the kind of the purely kind of
system it's maybe due to some kind of a
errors in the other part so we can
easily identify the issue and so on so I
recommend you guys to actually always
check the delion and number of the
divition and the insertion whether they
are extremely large in these cases there
are some kind of issues are not in the
kind of system level but some kind of
bug and so
on okay and then uh with this kind of
explanation I will move to the short
quiz
um can you yes
um so the
uh the quiz is to uh
compute this uh uh error
count and then uh report the
number uh the number can be 0 1 2 3 4
not 1 two 3 4 that's prob I remember but
anyway they're showing in the uh the P
now right yeah can you guys see the P
okay and Computing it by the way do not
speaking
okay Computing and then the the
uh uh
the submit your answer
equation is like
this yeah this is the answer
so this part of BR right and
the we have a three
possibility from here to here uh the 1 +
1 becomes two from here to here 1 + 1
becomes two from here to here the zero
plus uh the the local distance and that
is actually correct so it's actually
zero so this part 0 versus two versus
two and the minimum is zero so this
becomes zero and then the move to the
this next one uh 2 + 1 becomes 3 0 + 1
becomes one and one plus uh this one uh
C and that is different so it's actually
accumulated one so one versus two versus
three and each other goes to one uh and
so on so by doing that uh we can
actually fill out all the table and we
can get the all the kind of error
account
okay
yes it's basically the the the
the I then the written here basically
the just a Chon Dela whether it is the
correct or not so that's why the the the
correct case is zero why I kind of be
making it a little bit kind of abstract
this is because some cases we can
actually using a different uh the the uh
the methodic for for here so like even
for example the uh the word is slightly
different the character is similar and
then local sub uh will be changed and so
on but anyway generally it is zero
one
okay and the don't worry that you guys
can enjoy more in the big table in the
homework a little bit T yeah okay uh so
I will move to the uh several other the
metcs and for on so we usually using
this kind of word ER or character er and
Computing with edit distance but there
are several other measures for example
the uh the last the the the ASR example
the some of the errors are actually
sound similar right but just the word is
different and so on in this Cas is uh
probably the model itself is not so bad
but model to kind of converting the the
the phone information to the word this
function may not be strong
so to measure this kind of part people
also using p error and some other errors
are also proposed but generally for
error the character error word error and
sometimes sentence error are often used
in measure and I
of use this Tool St
sctk needs to switch the scoring to kit
because this are kind of very wellknown
standardized tool kit so I actually
often that I want to mention that metc
is super important right if there is a
bug in the metric it will be disaster
right that the your kind of a result and
our result potentially it can be same
but if there a bug and then it becomes
different we cannot compare the the the
our result and so on so setting the
methodic is it's very important part
component of the science and the the N
is actually
standardization the uh the the working
on the standardization National
Institute and it's actually providing
this kind of scoring tool they are also
the providing by the way other kind of
unit like atomic clock and so on is also
the managed by this uh the by using this
kind of standardized tool we can safely
evaluate the our the the the methodic so
I recommend you guys to actually be
careful about using some kind of
evalation measure that is my kind of one
suggestion and
the this uh the graph I often will show
you the this is a quite kind of a the
typical graph in speech history so the
this the Y AIS is quate lower is better
and the x axis is
here and this result is actually using
the same
Corpus and then every year researchers
are kind of using different techniques
or more data but at least that always
kind of setting the same test set and
the same evaluation Mets and then what's
happening is that we can compare the
performance easily so this sounds very
kind of the the the straight forward
right but it's actually this uh the kind
of cases uh do not happen in the other
area but speech cases we actually knew
that this kind of evaluation is very
important and actually this uh the the
competition uh they quite widely used
even in the 1990s so that we actually
the accumulating the uh the the
Technologies and we can actually easily
can get the kind of benefit of deep
running so there are several kind of
stories but speech is one of the first
area that's showing that deep running is
performing quite well because of this
kind of benchmarking same evaluation
metc and we can easily compare the
performance so this is the kind of the
the area that people may call that
speech condition is easy because we can
easily
evaluate our system is better or not
based on what again it sounds like very
kind of preval but it's actually not uh
the other speech processing area or the
other many of the machine learning
applications it is actually not true
like for example even for the speech
area speech synthesis it is very
difficult to evaluate whether the
created speech is good or not good May
means that the the sounds better or
sound kind of a correctly which is
different and we also need to ask people
to listen so this is very very kind of
painful and the time consum same for the
spoken di systems we are not sure that
what is the kind of best spoken D system
it can be answered quickly or it can
answer the kind of correct answers it's
uh the answer the friendly it's
depending on our kind of the the the
applications uh actually what we want
the system to do is very different and
again it's not like an absolute measure
compared with the speech condition and
the same for speech
enhancement and so on so this are due to
this speech is widely used not just
because this is a good application but
also because that it is a very good
machine learning a benchmark so many
actually researchers machine learning
researchers after they develop a very
techniques they apply the speech again
with that we can easily evaluate the
performance and so
on the if we gu that this some other
measures and so on like a blue or other
measures and so on you some of you may
know that you know this is not really
correlated to this the the subjective uh
evalation but speech performance what is
quite C
but this means that we need a
transcription right to compute that kind
of a speech we need a kind of difference
and then hypothesis and then we could
compute a kind of error right so
actually the transcription is important
uh whether to evalate ASR result is
correct or not and of course the speech
condition is now becom kind of compet
machine learning the problem which means
that the supervis training is very
important
and the transcription is again very
important so to evaluate the SR and to
kind of train the model anyway a
transcription is important correct
transcription is
important so now I kind of move to how
to obtain the
transcription so to explain about kind
of how to obtain the transcription I
will also explain about the two types of
the speech uh the database
one uh is uh let speech and the other is
the spontaneous speech and depending on
this type actually whether we can access
to the transcription or not is very
different so first are the what is r to
speech I think I have a example here
hope it would
be has been moving in tandem with the
mark recently
and this one is actually spontaneous
speech
okay you you have long I gu not
ra
and he began a confused complaint
against the wizard who had vanished
behind the curtain on the
left can you listen to the audio okay
good and the third one is the very
famous database called liy speech and
this is actually de speech this actually
audio book and then some people actually
reading actually reading the book so
whether we kind of read some kind of a
the the uh the text or just kind of
having a conversation and recording and
then the speech of course the speech
style is uh very different but actually
that in terms of the transcription
access uh this is also very
different okay uh let's move to the uh
let speech uh cases uh let speech cases
uh we just read that
sentence so this is actually easy to
correct we just ask people to
read and also uh it is easy to
anonymize because this
sentence maybe may not be very related
to this kind of personal information
right of course voice can have some kind
of privacy but the content doesn't have
any kind of information so actually this
is also easy to
anonymize so this is actually one of the
easiest way to collect the
data however the critical issue is that
it's not our usual speech it's not a
real
conversation and then uh the other
option is to actually uh transcribe the
recording
this is a kind of a probably most kind
of the uh the realistic way to get our
speech and corresponding a
transcription but it is very
expensive um that's actually for example
the switchboard audio which I kind of
played as a spontaneous speech example
uh it's if there's no kind of training
it just two minutes of the audio uh the
if we try to transcribe it takes 30
minutes or even longer and so
on and it's actually getting more
difficult if the moving to the kind of
the uh the the the case that microphone
is far from the uh the the original uh
the cross talk microphone setup in this
case uh actually the data is quite
distorted and then the the data is
the uh the speeches the very
noisy but this also happens in the our
real kind of the scenario and this are
the is the case that you know I show the
demonstration right I kind of are having
the the demonstration with a lot of
noises but they can actually well kind
of transcribe the data this is actually
partly because uh they have a
transcription if in this kind of noise
situation and I will again play several
kind of audio uh this is the one of the
audio that they collected in the project
called Chim three which I am involved
in a year earlier GM Hughes had first
quarter
profit base rates are The Benchmark for
commercial
sources say at least two BS had some
doubts about City performance
numbers rates are expected to remain at
those levels move a little higher this
week the treasury Department's quarterly
auction this is one project I collected
data and the other project I also
collected similar data and this previous
project called chime 3 start version of
kind of a very noisy speech uh the
recognition project and this is six uh
six
version
Oh ideas about what to
do put
already is all the effort needed
tired
TI first this one and this one which one
do you think it's easy to
transcribe time three or CH six which
one do you think it's easier yeah time
three right yeah time six is you know
are the the many people are speaking
each other conversation so it is
actually very difficult and then the uh
second uh quiz uh I want to check the
result actually
I'm happy to see that everyone is
correct it's kind of obvious but now you
understand what is r to speech and what
is you know the noisy speech right it's
actually very cool this project we ask
the people to actually WR the sentence
in this kind of scenario so people are
very painful because you know the there
are lot of other people also here and
they have to read a sentence and answer
it so the two are the transcribe the
audio
uh I use the audacity uh which is
actually developed here at the CMU how
many people have ever used
audacity okay cool not so many people
but it's sufficient and there are
several other to like web ster or Adobe
Audition and so on so or several other
transcription tool and then we can
actually the transcribe it and how to do
it I just kind of making a de the video
of how to transcribe uh by using the AAC
City okay so
first
that specify the segment create the
audio and
then specify the audio
this is by the way F of the
[Laughter]
homework and it doesn't take so long
time but just you I want you guys to
know the experience this so um so yes
the answer is that even human we have to
dialy and recognize and the system also
have to do it so uh the the we have a
lot of speech data uh and I kind of
listing this kind of speech data but
there are three category uh one is kind
of the several
institution collect the data and release
it and this are kind of I say classical
style and LDC is the most important uh
most kind of famous The Institute to
collect the data or get the kind of data
from the data provider and release it
and this part there are lot of kind of
famous old database and so on so if you
want to actually use this data uh please
let me know because Let's uh because the
LD cm is a member of the LDC and you
guys actually can potentially get this
the data
free but of course that it's centralized
with some of the faculties and so on so
it's better to ask
me and there are several other other the
the way to kind of
uh the correct uh the the uh the get the
kind of speech data find the speech data
the other is the web based uh the the uh
the resources and here usually we can
get this data free and then the also
license can be less restrict permissive
license and the other is the YouTube and
the podcast and so on this has a that
you can download it but license is kind
of little bit gray so be careful about
how to use it especially when use it for
the research or even commercial and so
on it's basically it's very difficult to
use uh but we still have a lot of
resources so why not we try to
use and the other other comment uh we
often use the uh the unit hour for the
speech so like for example I often use
you know that we have a thousand hours
of data which means a thousand is
actually large you guys may not have
sense right that thousand is are kind of
large we can start to make a commercial
product 100 hour is not very large but
we can start to make a speech cons
system anyway and less than 100 it's
starting to very difficult to make a
speech con system uh and we may need to
for example combine it with the
pre-training fine tuning strategies and
so on so this are that happens in a lot
of low resource languages usually the
data it less than 10000 yeah